U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation Records
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation Records
1940 - c. 1955
1942 - 1945
npkmc-236-071
Prenting, Theodore
Prenting, Peter H.
U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation
Valetor Deluxe Cleaners
5 Linear Feet
U.S. Hoffman was the successor company to what started out as the Hoffman Pressing Machine Company in Syracuse, NY in 1904. By the 1930s, the U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corp was one of the largest producers of a full line of laundry and dry cleaning machinery in the United States. In 1936, U.S. Hoffman opened a new plant in Poughkeepsie, NY, while maintaining their main plant in Syracuse. The U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation Records consists of production and promotional documents, letters, photographs, audiovisual material, U.S. Navy and government correspondence, an Army-Navy “E” Award pennant, and munitions relating to the business of the U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation once located in Poughkeepsie,
Marist College Archives and Special Collections 3399 North Road Poughkeepsie, NY Poughkeepsie New York 12601 United States
No Restrictions
U.S. Hoffman was the successor company to what started out as the Hoffman Pressing Machine Company in Syracuse, NY in 1904. By the 1930s, the U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corp was one of the largest producers of a full line of laundry and dry cleaning machinery in the United States.
In 1936, U.S. Hoffman opened a new plant in Poughkeepsie, NY, while maintaining their main plant in Syracuse. The Poughkeepsie plant was located at 18 Violet Avenue. Before the outbreak of WWII, the Poughkeepsie Plant produced a variety of equipment for the commercial/industrial laundry/dry cleaning industries.
Shortly after the start of WWII, the Poughkeepsie Plant produced a number of mobile, truck mounted laundries that could be placed in rear areas of combat zones for use by the Quartermaster Corps. However, this plan was quickly dropped, as the Plant was converted to produce desperately needed munitions. Starting about June 1942, the Poughkeepsie plant began manufacturing the projectiles for 40mm anti-aircraft shells and continued this work until August 1945. During this time period, almost 15 million projectiles were made, and the Plant received the Army-Navy E Award, with two subsequent stars, for excellence in production. This Award was given to only about 3% of all war production plants in WWII, and fewer yet to receive subsequent stars. Approximately 600 people worked at the Poughkeepsie Plant during the war years, and the Plant Manager during the entire period 1936-1947 was Peter H. Prenting, a Poughkeepsie resident.
After the War, the Plant returned to its usual peace time production of laundry/dry cleaning machinery and continued in operation until August 1947, when the Hoffman Corporation decided to consolidate all its NY laundry/dry cleaning machinery production at its main plant in Syracuse, N.Y.
A portion of this collection documents another Poughkeepsie business known as Valetor Deluxe Cleaners and Dyers. The founding of Valetor Deluxe was a direct result of the decision by U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation to close their Poughkeepsie Plant. The former Plant Manager, Prenting, an engineer by profession, decided that he did not wish to relocate his family to Syracuse. Instead, he and his family, opened their new dry cleaning business.
The Valetor Deluxe Cleaners and Dryers opened in April 1948, and the business started with a store and two-story plant on Hooker Avenue. This Plant was expanded several times in subsequent years to accommodate the growing full-service dry cleaners. Valetor ultimately provided dry cleaning, shirt laundering, carpet cleaning, tailoring, invisible reweaving, in-house leather glove and apparel cleaning and dying, wedding gown cleaning and preservation, fur cleaning and storage, upholstery cleaning, drapery cleaning, lampshade cleaning, and an interior car cleaning service.
Valetor quickly became the second largest dry cleaning establishment in Dutchess County and typically employed about 20 full time people. The Prenting Family were all involved in the business from the outset. Mary Prenting, wife, was involved through much of the life of the Company. Daughter, Marta, worked part or full time for a couple years, and, son, Theodore (Ted) worked part time while in high school, subsequently studied at the National Institute of Dry Cleaning in Silver Spring, MD, and managed plant operations or sales for the business for a total of about five years.
When Peter Prenting passed away in May, 1963, his son, Theodore, temporarily returned from his research position at IIT Research Institute, Chicago, and managed the business until it could be sold in May, 1964. The new owners were Isidor Haitkin and Abraham Marinoff, both from Long Island, who relocated to Poughkeepsie. They owned the business until May 1974, when the Hooker Avenue Plant and Store were damaged in a devastating fire. The business never reopened.
The U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation Records consists of production and promotional documents, letters, photographs, audiovisual material, US Navy and government correspondence, an Army-Navy “E” Award pennant, and munitions relating to the business of the US Hoffman Machinery Corporation once located in Poughkeepsie, NY. The U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation Records also contain 35mm slides and captions about Valetor Deluxe Cleaners and Dyers.
U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corp.; Valetor Deluxe Cleaners and Dyers; World War II; Weapons industry
Collection is arranged into two series: 1) U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation and 2) Valetor Deluxe Cleaners and Dyers
The U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation Records was donated to Marist College and Special Archives by Theodore Prenting, former Marist faculty and son of Peter H. Prenting. Peter H. Prenting was a U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation Plant Manager from 1936 to 1947.
- U.S. Hoffman Machinery Corporation, 1941-1945
  This series consists of production and promotional documents, letters, photographs, audiovisual material, US Navy and government correspondence, an Army-Navy “E” Award pennant, and munitions relating to the business of the US Hoffman Machinery Corporation once located in Poughkeepsie, NY.
  - U.S. Hoffman Job Clipping, 1944-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Hoffman 40mm Production Chart and Promotional Material, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Munitions – 40 mm projectile and shell [Placeholder - See Box 3], circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Munitions – 40 mm projectile only [Placeholder; See Box 3], circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Hoffman DVD-Film Transfer, WWII Industrial Film DVD, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Manufacturer's Association of Poughkeepsie-Clambake and Outing (Photograph) [Placeholder - See Box 2], 1944-08-17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Large Group of Men at Celebratory Event (Photograph), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dutchess County Fair, 1905-04-28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Army Navy Production Award Description, 2003-01-25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Navy and Government Correspondence, 1942; 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - US Navy Correspondence; Peter H. Prenting's Acceptance Comments, 1905-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Congratulatory Letters to Hoffman from other Companies, 1905-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - List of Employees eligible to receive "E" Award, 1905-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Army-Navy "E" Award Program and Pin, 1944-04-28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Army-Navy "E" Award Celebration Photograph of Employee Usherettes, 1905-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Flag [Placement Holder - See Box 2], 1905-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Valetor Deluxe Cleaners and Dyers, 1952-1955
  This series contains 35mm slides of the Valetor Deluxe Cleaners and Dyers.
  - Valetor Deluxe Cleaners and Dyers 35mm slides, circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Valetor Deluxe Cleaners Women's Sponsored Bowling Team (Photograph), circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)